Ricardo Cruz, PhD







(D) 0000-0002-5189-6228

Ricardo Cruz received a B.S. degree in computer science and an M.S. degree in applied mathematics, both from the University of Porto, Portugal. Since 2015, he has been a researcher at INESC TEC working in machine learning with particular emphasis on computer vision. He earned his Ph.D. in Computer Science in 2021 with a special emphasis on computer vision and deep learning. Currently, he is a post-doctoral researcher on autonomous driving under the THEIA research project, a partnership between the University of Porto and Bosch Car Multimedia.

SKILLS: Python \cdot C \cdot C++ \cdot Java \cdot R \cdot MATLAB \cdot PyTorch \cdot TensorFlow \cdot OpenCV \cdot $SQL \cdot Git$



EDUCATION _

2021 Ph.D. Computer Science (joint degree University of Porto, Minho and Aveiro)

2015 M.Sc. Mathematical Engineering (University of Porto)

2012 B.Sc. Computer Science (University of Porto)

EMPLOYMENT _

Post-doctoral Researcher on Autonomous Driving University of Porto 2021-... (FEUP) [in partnership with Bosch]

Research Assistant on Machine Learning and Computer Vision INESC 2015-2021 TEC

Research Grant on Mathematical Modelling Research Mathematics Cen-2014 ter of the University of Porto (CMUP)

Teaching ____

Invited Auxiliary Professor, University of Porto (FEUP) 2021 - 2022

2018–2021 Invited Teacher Assistant, University of Porto (FEUP)

Courses _

The teaching consisted of the pratical lessons (2h-4h per week) and helping with the materials.

- L.EIC003: Programming Fundamentals (Python) [L.EIC] (2018/2019, 2019/2020, 2020/2021, 2021/2022)
- L.EIC009: Programming (C/C++) [L.EIC] (2019/2020, 2020/2021)
- L.EEC009: Data Structures and Algorithms (C/C++) [L.EEC] (2021/2022)

Last update: May 23, 2023

Awards

- **2022** Bosch for Mobility: My students won Best New Participating Team in an autonomous driving competition ⋄
- **2021 INESC TEC Outstanding Recognition Award:** Monthly award for INESC TEC collaborators, for maintenance of the HPC infrastructure *♥*
- 2021 Pedagogic award (voted by students): University of Porto (FEUP)
- 2021 Best paper and presentation: RECPAD conference
- **2018** INESC TEC Outstanding Recognition Award: Monthly award for INESC TEC collaborators, for organizing workshops *⋄*
- 2017 Kaggle Bronze Medal (competition) and Silver (engagement)

PARTICIPATION IN SCIENTIFIC PROJECTS _____

- **THEIA** Automated Perception Driving (POCI-01-0247-FEDER-047264)
- CLARE Computer-aided cervical cancer screening (POCI-01-0145-FEDER-028857)
- NanoSTIMA Macro-to-Nano Human Sensing: Towards Integrated Multimodal Health Monitoring and Analytics (NORTE-01-0145-FEDER-000016)

IMPACT AND CITATIONS

- Google Scholar (may/2023): 171 citations, 7 h-index ♂
- Web of Science (may/2023): 73 citations, 4 h-index &
- Scopus (may/2023): 111 citations, 5 h-index &

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS _____

- 1. **R. Cruz**, D. Silva, T. Gonçalves, D. Carneiro, J. Cardoso (2023). Two-Stage Framework for Faster Semantic Segmentation. *MDPI Sensors* •
- 2. T. Albuquerque, L. Rosado, **R. Cruz**, M. Vasconcelos, T. Oliveira, J. Cardoso (2023). Rethinking Low-Cost Microscopy Workflow: Image Enhancement using Deep Based Extended Depth of Field Methods. *Elsevier Intelligent Systems with Applications*
- 3. T. Albuquerque, R. Cruz, J. Cardoso (2022). Quasi-Unimodal Distributions for Ordinal Classification. MDPI Mathematics
- 4. T. Albuquerque, R. Cruz, J. Cardoso (2021). Ordinal Losses for Classification of Cervical Cancer Risk. PeerJ Computer Science ⋄
- 5. R. Prates, R. Cruz, A. Marotta, R. Ramos, E. Filho, J. Cardoso (2019). Insulator visual non-conformity detection in overhead power distribution lines using deep learning. Springer Journal Computers & Electrical Engineering ⋄
- 6. R. Cruz, K. Fernandes, J. Costa, M. Pérez Ortiz, J. Cardoso (2018). Binary ranking for ordinal class imbalance. Springer Journal Pattern Analysis and Applications &

CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

My favorite publications are in highlight.

1. P. S. Silva, R. Cruz, ASM Shihavuddin, T. Gonçalves (2023) [ACCEPTED]. Interpretability-Guided Human Feedback During Neural Network Training. Springer Iberian conference on pattern recognition and image analysis (Ibpria)

Last update: May 23, 2023 Page 2 of 4

- 3. R. Cruz, R. Prates, E. Filho, J. Costa, J. Cardoso (2021). Background Invariance by Adversarial Learning. *IEEE 25th International Conference on Pattern Recognition* (ICPR)
- 4. R. Cruz, J. Costa, J. Cardoso (2019). Automatic Augmentation by Hill Climbing. Springer 28th International Conference on Artificial Neural Networks (ICANN) €
- 5. R. Cruz, J. Costa, J. Cardoso (2019). Averse Deep Semantic Segmentation. *IEEE 41st Engineering in Medicine and Biology Conference (EMBC)*
- 6. R. Cruz, M. Silveira, J. Cardoso (2018). A Class Imbalance Ordinal Method for Alzheimer's Disease Classification. *IEEE International Workshop on Pattern Recognition in Neuroimaging (PRNI) №*
- 7. K. Fernandes, R. Cruz, J. Cardoso (2018). Deep image segmentation by quality inference. *IEEE International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN)*
- 8. R. Cruz, K. Fernandes, J. Costa, J. Cardoso (2017). Constraining type II error: building intentionally biased classifiers. Springer International Work-conference on Artificial Neural Networks (IWANN) &
- 9. M. Pérez-Ortiz, K. Fernandes, R. Cruz, J. Cardoso (2017). Fine-to-coarse ranking in ordinal and imbalanced domains: an application to liver transplantation. Springer International Work-conference on Artificial Neural Networks (IWANN) &
- 10. R. Cruz, K. Fernandes, J. Costa, M. Pérez-Ortiz, J. Cardoso (2017). Combining ranking with traditional methods for ordinal class imbalance. Springer International Work-conference on Artificial Neural Networks (IWANN) ❖
- 11. **R. Cruz**, K. Fernandes, J. Costa, M. Pérez-Ortiz, J. Cardoso (2017). Ordinal class imbalance with ranking. *Springer Iberian conference on pattern recognition and image analysis (Ibpria) ❷*
- 12. R. Cruz, K. Fernandes, J. Costa, J. Cardoso (2016). Tackling class imbalance with ranking. *IEEE International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN)*

Jury Participation _

- **2022** Mafalda Oliveira: Neuroblastoma Cancer Radiogenomics (FEUP, External Examiner)
- **2022** João Pedro Fonseca: AI-Based Models to Predict The Traumatic Brain Injury Outcome (FEUP, External Examiner)
- **2022** Ana Maria Sousa: Learning to write medical reports from EEG data (FEUP, Chairman)
- 2022 Bruno Nascimento: Detection and classification of small impacts on vehicles based on deep learning algorithms (U. Minho, External Examiner)
- **2021** Artur Ferreira: 3D Lung Computed Tomography Synthesis using Generative Adversarial Networks (FCUP, External Examiner)
- **2021** Vítor Figueiredo: Feasibility of using autoencoders for learning car interior background models (U. Minho, External Examiner)

on-going Rafael Cristino: Introducing Domain Knowledge to Autonomous Driving (FEUP) on-going Alankrita Asthana: Iterative Inference for Point-Clouds (TUM, Munich)

- on-going José Guerra (with L. Teixeira): Academic Internship in Out of Distribution Detection – Autonomous Driving (Internship at Bosch Car Multimedia) (FEUP)
- 2022 Pedro Silva (with T. Gonçalves): Human Feedback during Neural Networks Training (FEUP) \mathcal{O}
- João Silva: Environment Detection for Railway Applications based on Automotive Technology (Internship at Continental) (FEUP)
- Ana Bezerra (with J. Costa): Phishing Detection with a Machine Learning Net (Internship at E-goi) (FCUP)

B.Sc. Projects Supervisions _

- **2022** Diana Silva (with T. Gonçalves): Semantic Segmentation in Neural Networks using Iterative Visual Attention
- **2022** Filipe Campos, Francisco Cerqueira, Vasco Alves: *Mobile App using Object Detection for Car Driving*
- 2022 Bruno Gomes, Rafael Camelo: Internship at ANO